<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Being for ever with the Lord, the great hope, end and comfort of believers what it is, and how to be obtained and forethought of / preached by Matthew Sylvester ; and published at the publick request of Mr. Ri. Baxter, at the hearing of it.</title>
            <author>Sylvester, Matthew, 1636 or 7-1708.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62089</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6329</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34636</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14525438</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14525438</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102539</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62089)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102539)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1073:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Being for ever with the Lord, the great hope, end and comfort of believers what it is, and how to be obtained and forethought of / preached by Matthew Sylvester ; and published at the publick request of Mr. Ri. Baxter, at the hearing of it.</title>
                  <author>Sylvester, Matthew, 1636 or 7-1708.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], iv, 88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Robinson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXVIII [1688]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Thessalonians, 1st, IV, 17 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Mystical union.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102539:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102539:1"/>
            <p>BEING <hi>For ever with the Lord,</hi> THE Great Hope, End and Comfort of BELIEVERS: What it is, and how to be obtained and forethought of.</p>
            <p>Preached by MATTHEW SYLVESTER, And Publiſhed at the publick Requeſt of Mr. <hi>Ri. Baxter,</hi> at the hearing of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Robinſon,</hi> at the Golden Lion in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. M.DC.LXXXVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:102539:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:102539:2"/>
            <head>TO Mr. M. SYLVESTER'S HEARERS.</head>
            <p>IF you know not the Reaſons of my deſiring Mr. <hi>S.</hi> at the hearing of it, to publiſh this Sermon, I now tell you, they were theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> I was affected with it, as ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to my own Condition; who have little Comfort to live on, but my hopes of <hi>being for ever with the Lord,</hi> and no Motive ſo powerful to engage me to my great Duty, and to overcome all Temptations.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> And that which is ſo ſuitable to me, is not unſuitable to you: I am not the only Man that muſt die, and
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:102539:3"/> that hath another Life to live.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Mr. <hi>Sylveſter's</hi> Style is ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, and naturally elegant, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I nor you can ſufficiently digeſt his Sermons upon a tranſient hearing: A full and frequent review may make them more our own: Of-times four or five <hi>Names,</hi> or Epithets, ſignify as much as ſo many diſtinct Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and his Phraſes are not always vulgar: And therefore they are like ſtrong Meat, that muſt have longer time, than lighter, for digeſtion.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> The Subject is ſuch as you muſt daily live upon, and therefore ſhould be glad of a daily Help for your pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Meditations on it. <hi>Being for ever with Chriſt in Glory,</hi> is that which you pray for, hope for, labour for, ſuffer and wait for, deny the Fleſh and the World for, and which you muſt fetch your ſupporting com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts from, or elſe you muſt have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Hope nor Comfort, which ſound awakened Reaſon can own.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="vii" facs="tcp:102539:3"/>
               <hi>5.</hi> As it is a diſcouragement to Preachers, when the beſt ſtudied Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, are forgotten at the Church-doore; ſo it is a great mercy to Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers when they may carry home, and keep, and daily uſe, ſuch excellent and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Helps. If the <hi>Devil</hi> knew what Printing was like to do againſt his Kingdom, I wonder that he did no more to hinder the inventing of it: It was becauſe the Father of Lights reſtrained him. You Printers and Bookſellers look well to your ſelves, for next to Magiſtrates and Miniſters, there are few that Devils have more malignant deſigns upon than you, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>ſilence</hi> your Preſſes and Shops as to Good, or to open them to Evil. You ſpeak more publickly than Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits do. To many Thouſands you either preach wholſom ſaving Truth, or vend flagitious and pernicious Evil. If you vend the beſt Books only for Mony, you have your Reward; yet thouſands may have a greater gain;
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:102539:4"/> as carnal Preachers may periſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves while their Hearers are ſaved.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I would have thoſe Men that have thought our ſilencing theſe <hi>28</hi> Years to be the Churches Intereſt, and have called on their Rulers to ſtrike home, to ſee what Doctrine it is that we preach, and whether it deſerve Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and Deſtruction. If many ſuch Sermons tell them not, they may ſee it in the larger Writings, of Mr. <hi>Ant. Burges,</hi> Mr. <hi>Richard</hi> and <hi>Joſeph Allen,</hi> Dr. <hi>Manton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Charnock,</hi> and many more, (to paſs by the yet living).</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servant, <hi>RI. BAXTER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102539:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Theſſ. iv. 17. latter Part.</hi>
                  </bibl> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. —And ſo ſhall we ever be with the Lord.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THeſe words are a part of thoſe cheering Paſſages which were written to this excellent and much-commended Church, by way of Antidote againſt immoderate Sorrows for ſuch as ſleep in Jeſus. And indeed the provident Care and miniſterial Faithfulneſs of this great Apoſtle, clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appears in the Matter, Order, and Vigour of Expreſſion that this Epiſtle entertains its Reader with. He firſt acknowledges what effectual Grace had brought them to, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.2-10. Hethen appeals to God and them, as to his Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, Doctrines, and deportment in both their genuine, deſigned, and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesful references to their Good, 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:102539:5"/> ii. 1-20. Then (when he was to ſtay alone at <hi>Athens;</hi> for which no doubt he ſaw great cauſe) he ſends <hi>Timotheus</hi> to them for their Eſtabliſhment and Conſolation in the Faith; and to obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate all Diſcouragements and Snares which otherwiſe might make them droop or ſtumble. And <hi>Timothy</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns with a very good account con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them; which ſends our Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to his Knees again, with Thanks and Joys, and further Supplications for them, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> iii. 1-13. And then he preſſes them to walk according to his Doctrine, and abundantly to improve that Chriſtian Directory which they had received from him for pleaſing God: to avoid all polluting Sins (all Sins are ſuch, but ſome incomparably more ſo than others) as inconſiſtent with their Heavenly Intereſts and Hopes, or prejudicial thereto, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive thereof, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> iv. 1-12. And then when they are under provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential Preſſures, let them repair unto the Hopes &amp; Comforts of their return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102539:5"/> Lord from Heaven, and of their abode with him and his whole Family for ever, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> iv. 13-18. and let them alſo make their higheſt practical Improvements hereof, as being under better Circumſtances ſo to do, than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> v. 1-22. All which he cloſes with a ſolemn Prayer and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nediction, with teſtified aſſurance of ſucceſs herein, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.23, 24. and hereupon he <hi>charges them by the Lord, that this Epiſtle be read to all the Holy Brethren,</hi> verſ. 27. as being of ſuch conſequence and concernment to them all. And hence you may ſee how this great Apoſtle guards his Conſolations; in firſt ſecuring Chriſtianity in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Practice of it, and then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding to encourage and refreſh the Hearts of Mourners. Hence then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Text it ſelf, in its,
<list>
                  <item>I. Senſe.</item>
                  <item>II. Evidence.</item>
                  <item>III. Uſefulneſs.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:102539:6"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> The Senſe of the Text.</head>
               <p>And here theſe things occur'd to be conſidered (tho briefly) in their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. 1. The Perſons determined to this Priviledg. <hi>We who are found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live,</hi> and <hi>the Dead in Chriſt that riſe firſt,</hi> verſ. 16, 17. and all of them <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Light and Day,</hi> 1 Theſſ. v. 5, 8, 9. The living Members and true Favorites of Chriſt, diſtinguiſhed from mere Pretenders, Enemies and Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, by their true conformity to Chriſt himſelf, in Spirit, Purpoſe, and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour. 2. The Priviledg and State whereto they are determined, <hi>to be for ever with the Lord.</hi> 3. The Time and Manner of their entrance into the full poſſeſſion of this State. <hi>Chriſt comes</hi> deſcending with <hi>a ſhout from Heaven, the Voice of the Arch-Angel, and with the Trump of God. The Dead in Chriſt riſe firſt: They with the Living are caught up to meet Chriſt in the Air, and ſo they are for ever with him,</hi> ver. 16, 17.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:102539:6"/>1. The Perſons here intended for this bleſſed State, and reckoning duly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon; <hi>We.</hi> How careful was this Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle-eyed Apoſtle to prevent a Rape upon a thing ſo chaſt and ſacred as this our Chriſtian Hope! <hi>You turned to God from Idols, to ſerve the living and true God, and to wait for his Son from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 1.9, 10. <hi>Your Work of Faith, Labour of Love, and Patience of Hope in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, in the ſight of God and our Father: knowing—your E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of God,</hi> verſ. 3, 4. It is not every one that is to be with Chriſt for ever. The Subject muſt be ſuited to this State and Priviledg; and that, not by mere Miracle, but by the fit im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements of thoſe Means and Helps which God affords us for our preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on-work. Means ſuited to their Ends are to be adhered to, and uſed accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly. Nor can it be expected that God's Inſtitutions will ordinarily be neglected by himſelf, and that our neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect thereof ſhould be to us as proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, as our fit obſervation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:102539:7"/> And yet, miſtake me not, I do not ſay, that outward Means, and moral Swa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, are all that Chriſtian Converts are brought home by. There is a powerful quickning Divine touch upon the Soul, needful to make it throughly Chriſtian; and without this no Man becomes a real Chriſtian. And none can live with Chriſt for ever, but he that is wrought and kept thereto by ſpecial Grace and Providence. And excellent Perſons muſt ſuch be that are thus changed and kept for ſuch a bliſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful State as this here in the Text: The Apoſtle calls them, <hi>the Children of the Light and Day,</hi> 1 Theſſ. v. 5. ſuch as derive a new Nature from it, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> iii. 3, 18. walk under the Government and Conduct of it, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> v. 8. and are enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled to great Priviledges by it, <hi>Acts</hi> xx. 32. &amp; xxvi. 18. <hi>John</hi> xii. 35, 36. Let me then cloſe this Head with this; 1. Conſider who expreſly are to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, and upon what accounts, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> vi. 9, 10. <hi>Galat.</hi> v. 19-21. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> v. 5. <hi>Mat.</hi> xxv. 41-46. <hi>Rev.</hi> xxi. 8, 27. Hence
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102539:7"/> then this <hi>We</hi> can take in no ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. They that make nothing of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering directive, encouraging, and transforming Goſpel-Light; that have not fetch'd their Principles therefrom, and formed their Lives, and Practices, and Tempers thereunto, nor made the greateſt reckoning of theſe Privileges which are to be obtained thereby, are no ways fitted, and therefore not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined (whilſt ſuch) unto this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed State. Conſider, 2. whom Chriſt expreſly hath conſigned and promiſed this Priviledg unto; <hi>John</hi> xii. 26. <hi>Luk.</hi> xii. 31-37. &amp; xiv. 26, 27. &amp; xxii. 28-30. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> ii. 11, 12. <hi>Luke</hi> xxi. 36. 1 <hi>John</hi> iii. 1-3. &amp; <hi>Jude</hi> 20, 21. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> i. 5-11. &amp; iii. 14. 'Tis not the Form, but Power of Godlineſs, that can entitle and adopt us to that State: reſolute Promoters of Chriſt's Intereſts, patient Sufferers for it, prudent Contrivers, fruitful Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, ſuch as are obſervant of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, obedient to his Laws, ſubmiſſive to his Providence, and ſatisfied in and with his Care and Grace, and that joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102539:8"/> prepare and wait for his appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and preſence, and duly repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him to themſelves and others, ſo as to value nothing like him; no nor themſelves but as in him and for him. Theſe are to be with him for ever; ſee 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> iv. 6-8.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The State and Privilege whereto they are determined, <hi>to be for ever with the Lord,</hi> John xiv. 2, 3. Hence we are exhorted to <hi>ſeek thoſe things above where Chriſt is,</hi> Col. iii. 1. Hence, <hi>Come, ye Bleſſed</hi>—and <hi>depart from me, ye Curſed,</hi> Mat. xxv. 34, 41. <hi>Preſent with the Lord,</hi> 2 Cor. v. 8. <hi>They ſhall walk with me in White, for they are worthy,</hi> Rev. iii. 4. <hi>When Chriſt who is our Life ſhall appear, then ſhall we alſo appear with him in Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> Col. iii. 4. <hi>When he ſhall come to be glorified in his Saints, and admired at in all them that ſhall believe—in that Day,</hi> 2 Theſſ. i. 10. <hi>Father, I will that thoſe whom thou haſt given me, be with me where I am; that they may behold the Glory which thou haſt given me,</hi> John xvii. 24. <hi>Chriſt with his Father are
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102539:8"/> the only Temple</hi> of that Bleſſed State where all the Favorites of Chriſt muſt be, <hi>Rev.</hi> xxi. 23. Chriſt is <hi>our Life in Heaven,</hi> Col. iii. 3, 4. <hi>Our Hope from Heaven,</hi> Tit. ii. 13. Phil. iii. 20. <hi>Our Plea for Heaven,</hi> Heb. ix. 15. <hi>Our Way to Heaven,</hi> John xiv. 6. <hi>Our Head and all in Heaven,</hi> Epheſ. i. 20-23. We are to be with him who is the <hi>greateſt</hi> Friend, <hi>Iſa.</hi> ix. 6, 7. <hi>Heb.</hi> i. 2-14. &amp; iv. 14-16. <hi>Rev.</hi> i. 5, 18. <hi>Col.</hi> i. 15-19. &amp; ii. 9, 10. The <hi>deareſt</hi> Friend, <hi>Gal.</hi> ii. 20. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> iii. 18, 19. <hi>Tit.</hi> ii. 14. His aim at this our Exaltation and Advancement; his ſharp and coſtly Agonies and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements to effect it, and the delight he took therein, prove this. And the <hi>faſteſt</hi> and <hi>moſt faithful Friend,</hi> in <hi>Iſa.</hi> xi. 5. <hi>Heb.</hi> iii. 1, 2. &amp; x. 23. &amp; xiii. 8. But now what it is to be with Chriſt none yet fully know, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> xiii. 9-12. Chriſt himſelf tells us, <hi>We ſhall behold his Glory,</hi> John xvii. 22. Now what is Glory, but the luſter of diſcovered Excellency and Perfection? And O the excellence of the Lord-Redeemer,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102539:9"/> in his exalted State! his Transfigura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion amazed Beholders! When he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to <hi>Saul,</hi> he ſtruck him blind, the diſtant ſight or glance which <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi> got, impreſt no ordinary Majeſty and Glory on his Countenance. But Chriſt acquaints us with his three-fold Glory, wherein every Eye ſhall ſee him, <hi>Luke</hi> ix. 26. There is his perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Glory as to his humane Nature, <hi>a glorious Body;</hi> Spiritual, Immortal, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of Sufferings; lively, and of the neareſt alliance and approach to Spirit, and every way fitted to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Function of his compleated Soul; and (like a Chryſtal Mirror) to have his inward Glory tranſmitted through it to all Spectators. <hi>A glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soul,</hi> exerting all its vigours in and through this Body, wherein every Geſture, Look, and Motion, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, ſhall ſhew the excellent Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Furniture, and Beauty of his Soul. O the Wiſdom, Majeſty, Holineſs and Vivacity of his Soul, which then will have their fulleſt Explications and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances!
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102539:9"/> And then the <hi>fulneſs of the Godhead which dwells bodily in him,</hi> ſhall have ſuch great and clear Diſcoveries and Effects, as ſhall delightfully enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his Favorites with great varieties of diſcoveries for evermore. What emblemmatical Glory may attend his Perſon, as the Symbol and Signal of the extraordinary preſence of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him, and complacency in him, I dare not gueſs at, nor am I wiſe or good enough to know, nor arrogant and bold enough to determine: but ſure I am, the phyſical Changes, and the judicial Proceſs and Concluſions of that Day, with the evident yieldings and ſubmiſſions of the whole Frame of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to his Will, and the effectual bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of every Knee, and the confeſſion of every Tongue to him, will deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly bear the Character of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Glory, <hi>Phil.</hi> ii. 9-11. And all this ſhall we behold to everlaſting Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction. And we ſhall ſee his Glory further in all his Rectoral Excellencies. The Conſtitution and Adminiſtration
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102539:10"/> of his everlaſting Kingdom will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his Eminencies; How much he is above them in Excellencies and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives. How excellently he governs them, with ſuch extraordinary Light and Love, ſuited ſo accurately to their Capacities, Tempers, and Concerns, and every way preſerving all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and all their Entertainments and Employments, in all the harmony and decencies of a Divine Kingdom; and then how very kind he ever is and will be to them. Witneſs their conformity to his glorious Self, their intimate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation with him, and the inundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Delights that ever flow from him upon them; ſuch a Prince! ſuch Subjects! under ſuch Laws and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, and in ſuch order!</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Time and Manner of its Commencement. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Chriſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends, and we aſcend to meet him in the Air, and then we part no more: peruſe the Account hereof as given by inſpired Perſons; ſee <hi>Mat.</hi> xxv. 31-34. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> xv. 50-54. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> iv. 15-17.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102539:10"/> Then come thoſe Viſions, Diſpenſations, and Employments, and thoſe reciprocal Satisfactions, which cannot be but where Chriſt and his Favorites are got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and kept together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> The Evidence of this Truth.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Why elſe was Jeſus Chriſt Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate? <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14. <hi>He took not hold of Angels, but of the Seed of</hi> Abraham, <hi>Verſ.</hi> v. <hi>ib.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is there the word: and it is uſed of Chriſt when he took hold of timerous and ſinking <hi>Peter</hi> on the Waves, <hi>Mat.</hi> xiv. 31. No doubt but Chriſt's aſſuming to himſelf our Nature, was a great hold thereon. Such an alliance and approach to Man as intimated, yea demonſtrated, Chriſt's fitneſs and reſolution to be both viſible and delightfully converſible to all his Saints for ever, even in their own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Became Chriſt viſible that he might not be ſeen? Would he be Man to be eternally retired from humane view? We are told, that <hi>the Word was
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102539:11"/> made Fleſh, and dwelt amongst us, full of Grace and Truth; and that there were Eye-witneſſes of his Glory, the Glory as of the only begotten of the Father,</hi> John i. 14. And O how ample and empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical is this Paſſage, if well conſidered by us! and how pertinent and cogent as to the Caſe in hand! <hi>The Word;</hi> that living quickning Word, by whom God made the World and us, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> iii. 9. <hi>John</hi> v. 26. and whom God promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be the Root and Prince of Life, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> v. 11. by whom, and for whoſe pleaſure all Things both are and were created, <hi>Rev.</hi> iv. 11. and upheld, <hi>Heb.</hi> i. 2, 3. Who is the Image of the Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible God, the firſt-born of every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. See further, <hi>Col.</hi> i. 15-19. That Word which was to be, and was, and is his Father's Oracle to tell us fully what we are to know, be, do, avoid, and truſt to, <hi>Heb.</hi> i. 12. <hi>Acts</hi> iii. 22. <hi>Mat.</hi> xvii. 5. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> i. 16-18. Yea, and with whom, and what, and where we are to be for ever, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> i. 10. Whatever then this Word ſhall ſay,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102539:11"/> may we expect, and reſt upon, <hi>John</hi> i. 17, 18. <hi>Rev.</hi> iii. 7, 12, 14. Think here then upon that inſinuating charm of Speech; <hi>In my Father's Houſe are many Manſions—were it not ſo I would have told you</hi>—John xiv. 2, 3. <hi>This Word made Fleſh.</hi> See <hi>Heb.</hi> ii. 16-18. <hi>Rom.</hi> viii. 3, 4. and in that Tabernacle dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling amongſt Men: And why? that he might be our Kinſman, Surety, Brother, <hi>Heb.</hi> ii. 11-13. that he might thus be converſant and ſympathiſing with us, and ſtrike our <hi>very Hearts</hi> even through our <hi>very Senſes;</hi> and thereby make us fervently deſirous to be with him for ever. <hi>Good to be here,</hi> ſaid the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> when he had ſeen his Maſter's Glory in but a tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſient glimpſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> xvii. 4. And <hi>we ſaw his Glory—full of Grace and Truth. Grace poured into his Lips;</hi> and <hi>proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Majeſty, becauſe of Meekneſs, Truth, and Righteouſneſs,</hi> Pſal. xlv. 2-4, 6, 7. Iſa. xi. 2-5. And now, can we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that Chriſt ſhould meet us in our Nature, and tranſmit ſuch Glory to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102539:12"/> us through his very Fleſh; and thus allure us and conform us to himſelf, and ſo make us fit and long to be with him, and all to drop and leave us here?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Why elſe was Chriſt incarnate, ſo ſpirited, employed, and exerciſed, towards and for us, whilſt in this out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Court, <hi>Acts</hi> x. 36-40. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> ii. 21-27. <hi>Heb.</hi> xii. 2, 3. As to his <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Accompliſhments and Deportments,</hi> he was the Pattern of our Duty, and the Mirror of our Glory in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, <hi>Phil.</hi> ii. 5. 1 <hi>John</hi> ii. 6. with <hi>Phil.</hi> iii. 21. 1 <hi>John</hi> iii. 2. And as to his <hi>Sufferings</hi> he was the purchaſer of our Perſons and our Glory, that his own Grace and Name might thus be glorified in us, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> i. 12. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> vi. 20. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> i. 17-21. And wherefore all this waſte, if Chriſt and we muſt part at laſt? <hi>The Soul and Spirit is the Man;</hi> and if <hi>that</hi> be not right, the Joys and Treaſures of the Heavenly Kingdom cannot reliſh well, nor be eſteemed of to purpoſe. Hence, O the viſible Beauties of Chriſt's Soul! Such
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102539:12"/> Wiſdom in Self-conduct! ſuch Purity, Vigour, Tenderneſs, Sweetneſs, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, Sincerity, Fervour, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiality! How inwardly, evenly, readily, and chearfully was his Soul kept for God! and how entirely were his Thoughts taken up with God! And all to let us ſee what frame we muſt be in, for an eternal Fellowſhip with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in God: In him we ſee what Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit we muſt be of in Heaven. All his Converſation in this World was but the genuine Efforts of the devotedneſs and reſignedneſs of his Soul to God, and to the good of others by his Will. And all the Excellencies of humane Nature, that a right Spirit and Behaviour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God and Man could reach and ſhew, were ſo advanced and conſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in Chriſt, as that they challenged all Mens Obſervation, and bad defiance unto all Impeachments and Arraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.18. &amp; 8.29, 46. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> ii. 22. His Aim and Buſineſs was our confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to him in Sentiment, in Heart and Life, in this World, that he might
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102539:13"/> thus preſent us to his Father, as fitted for the Work and Joys of Heaven, and for the Freedoms and Delights of his own eternal Pretence. Never was hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature ſeen before, nor ſince, as it was in him. Such Knowledg of God! ſuch Wiſdom in the conduct of Affairs for God! ſuch Obedience and Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the Will of God! ſuch Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on God, Delight and Acquieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence in him! ſuch Expectations from him! and ſuch Fulfillings after him! <hi>John</hi> xvii. 4. theſe ſhew what Chriſt will bring us to, and ſo meet us in at laſt. And in this holy Courſe God met him with a ſweet Preluſion to his exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted State, and ordered <hi>Peter, James,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> to be Eye-witneſſes of his Glory in the Mount; and <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> to attend him, and to be clouded whilſt his Glory ſhone, <hi>Mat.</hi> xvii. 1-3. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> i. 16-18. Which Chriſt liked well, in that hereby it might appear, with whom we are to be for ever, and unto whom we ſhall be like. And as to his Sufferings and Death, they were the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102539:13"/> purchaſe of this State, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> i. 14. <hi>Heb.</hi> v. 9. &amp; ix. 15. &amp; ii. 9, 10. &amp; x. 20. The Expiation of our Crimes, the Ranſom of our Souls, and the Blood whereby we are conſecrated to this ſo glorious and delightful State; compare <hi>Luke</hi> xxiv. 26. with <hi>Heb.</hi> x. 19-22. &amp; xii. 24. If Chriſt then taught, did, ſuffered ſo much, that we might be both fit and ſure to be together: How can we doubt thereof, or miſs it? He knew what was in Man, what moſt affected him, and beſt became him: and what was the likelieſt way to ſuit Men to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and to the Viſions, Services, and Entertainments of that moſt glorious State and Kingdom where he himſelf now is, and will abide enthroned for ever. What Conſtitution &amp; Complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Souls and Perſons were to be brought unto: What Means and Helps would be moſt expedient hereunto. What Doctrines, Laws, and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges; what Ordinances and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential Diſpenſations would beſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate them in this Affair: In
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:102539:14"/> what Ways and Seaſons, and to what Degrees they ſhould be furniſhed and tried; and what would moſt effectually engage and keep them for his Father and himſelf. And hence we find his Name to be <hi>Wonderful Counſellor,</hi> Iſa. ix. 6. That in him are <hi>all the Treaſures of Wiſdom and Knowledg hidden,</hi> Col. ii. 3. <hi>That all the fulneſs of the God-head dwells bodily in him,</hi> verſ. 9. And that <hi>he is made of God Wiſdom to us,</hi> 1 Cor. i. 30. Under the conduct of this Wiſdom, he acquaints them with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>John</hi> xvii. 7, 8. He ſhews them his Commiſſion and Deſign, <hi>John</hi> vi. 38-40. Whither he was to go, and their way to follow him, <hi>Joh.</hi> xiv. 4-6. with all that might help or hinder them in their proficiency and advances towards his exalted Self, with all their needful Preparations for that State and Day wherein they ſhould behold him, and be with him, in his Meridian Glory, <hi>Luk.</hi> ix. 23-26. &amp; xii. 33-38. yea, and the coſt and gain of Chriſtian Godlineſs, <hi>Luk.</hi> xiv. 33. &amp; xviii. 29, 30. His evidently
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102539:14"/> great Love to them (with all Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Avouchments of it); this ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons all his Doctrines and Inſtructions, <hi>Joh.</hi> xiii. 1-15, 34, 35. &amp; xv. 8-17. He ſuffered long, was kind, vaunted not himſelf, was not puffed up, envied not, never behav'd himſelf unſeemly, ſought not his own, was not eaſily provoked, thought no Evil, rejoiced not in Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, but in the Truth, and in the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and advancement of his own unto himſelf. He bare all things, believed, hoped, and endured all things: (for thus doth Love, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> xiii. 4-7.) Thus hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhewed them what Spirit he was of, who was the brightneſs of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Glory: and how this Spirit ſtood and wrought towards them: and thus, how ſafely they might truſt him, and wherein their Tempers were to harmonize and accord with his, that ſo his Preſence might be their felicity and delight; then is he frequently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing with them about the Jubilee which they and he muſt keep together in the Heavens. Peter, <hi>thou ſhalt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:102539:15"/> me hereafter,</hi> John xiii. 36. <hi>Becauſe I live, ye ſhall live alſo:</hi> and, <hi>then you ſhall know that I am in my Father, and you in me, and I in you,</hi> Joh. xiv. 19, 20, 28. And <hi>becauſe I go to the Father, you ſhall ſee me,</hi> Joh. xvi. 16, 22. and <hi>I will come and fetch you to my ſelf,</hi> Joh. xiv. 3. And having li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as bound for Heaven, practically ſhewing His their way thereto, he dies, a Sacrifice for Sin, a Ranſomer of Souls, a Purchaſer of Heaven, a Conqueror of Death and Hell, a Martyr for the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Cauſe and Hope, a Patern and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empler of Patience, Fortitude, Holineſs and Hope, and Love to his; and can Chriſt loſe or leave us after all this?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Why elſe ſhould he in his raiſed and exalted State, aim ſo directly at this thing? for all that he hath ſpoken and done, and is ſtill doing, looks this way, <hi>Joh.</hi> xx. 17. How pertinently and copiouſly might we improve that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph! <hi>Epheſ.</hi> iv. 1-16. as the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement of this Truth and Hope, did not the ſtated Limits of a ſingle Sermon forbid it? Was Life and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102539:15"/> brought to Light by him, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to tantalize our Souls? 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> i. 10. Is it illuſtrated by the Goſpel to us as a State ſeparate from Chriſt himſelf? Muſt he, as Man, have it without us, or we without him? or muſt both have it in a State of Separation each from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? <hi>Was not Chriſt raiſed by his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that our Faith and Hope might be in God?</hi> 1 Pet. i. 21. And what is the Hope, that Chriſt and we ſhould ſee each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Face no more! Chriſt roſe not to continue here, for he was not ſuited to this groſs animal fading ſtate and frame of Things and Perſons: And would Chriſt ſhew himſelf on Earth alive, only to ſhew us what, and with whom we never are to be? as if he only came to raiſe our Expectations to our ſhame and horror? What was the ſenſe of that great Meſſage which he ſent by <hi>Mary</hi> to his Brethren? <hi>Go tell my Brethren I aſcend to my Father, and your Father; to my God, and your God,</hi> John xx. 17. What! Sons of God, and Brethren to Chriſt, and not live together with the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102539:16"/> ſame Father, and in the ſame Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and State! <hi>Heb.</hi> xi. 16. <hi>If Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, then Heirs: Heirs of God, and joint-Heirs with Chriſt; and to be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied together,</hi> Rom. viii. 17. <hi>What meant his entrance into Heaven as our Fore-runner?</hi> Heb. vi. 20. Was it to tell the glorious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of that bleſſed World, in all their heights of Wonderment and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, that he repented of this his glorious Enterprize, or that he was baffled in it, and that he cared not for having his Favorites and redeemed Ones in his ſight? What means his <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion</hi> there? <hi>Heb.</hi> vii. 25. &amp; ix. 24. whereby our Prayers, and Pains, and Hopes are ſo emboldned? <hi>Heb.</hi> x. 19-25, 35. &amp; ix. 12. Prays he againſt what he appeared, endeavoured and ſuffered for? or can he not prevail with God for us? or doth he trifle with his Father within the Veil, or ſport himſelf before his Courtiers there, with our deceiving and deluded Hopes? O ſuch Blaſphemy and Soloeciſm is there in theſe Thoughts, when they are matter of ſuſpicion and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:102539:16"/> belief, as that no ſober thinking Mind can entertain them! <hi>Why is he there en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throned?</hi> Heb. viii. 1. Mat. xxviii. 19, 20. <hi>Why made Head over all things to his Church?</hi> ſee <hi>Epheſ.</hi> i. 17-23. <hi>Addreſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by a dying Martyr for this thing, and he too owned ſignally,</hi> yea, miraculouſly in this his Martyrdom and Addreſs? <hi>Act.</hi> vi. 15. &amp; vii. 55-59. And why <hi>comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morated</hi> by his own ſpecial Order at the Table of the Lord, as one with whom we are to meet again as our Redeemer? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> xi. 23-26. Is not this priviledg ſealed and ſecured to us by the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace? How can the <hi>Amen,</hi> the <hi>faithful and true Witneſs,</hi> cheriſh and ſeal to deceitful Expectations? <hi>Heb.</hi> x. 23. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> ii. 10-13. What doth the Spirit of Jeſus form and ſeal us to but this? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> v. 5. &amp; i. 21, 22. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> i. 14. &amp; iv. 30. The Notions which he forms, the Faith which he works, the Tempers which he frames, the Deſires which he kindles, the Prayers and Labours which he animates, are all for this, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> ii. 13, 14. <hi>How can it be the dreadful doom
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102539:17"/> of all his Enemies to depart from him,</hi> if it be not our determined priviledg to be with him? <hi>Mat.</hi> xxv. 41. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> i. 9. <hi>Luk.</hi> xiii. 25-27. <hi>Did not Chriſt know that his moſt glorious Preſence would be a great Ingredient into the felicity of his Servants,</hi> as <hi>Jude</hi> 24, 25. aſſures us, and that <hi>our aſſimilation to him would be compleated</hi> (and continued) <hi>by the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of his State and Day,</hi> as his inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Servant hath informed us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> iii. 2. and that <hi>our reckoning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd longing after it, are the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="8 letters">
                        <desc>〈8 letters〉</desc>
                     </gap>ory Fruits of his own ſanctifying and ſealing Spirit,</hi> as we are told 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> v. 5-9. &amp; <hi>Rom.</hi> viii. 16-23. we had never been informed of ſuch a diſcriminating Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent in his final Sentence, as he hath told us of. <hi>Whence was it made the Charge and Buſineſs of his commiſſiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and inſpired Officers, to teach and enforce this grateful Truth upon us, were it not certainly decreed by God and Chriſt?</hi> 1 Cor. xv. 15. Col. iii. 4. 1 Theſſ. ii. 19. &amp; iii. 13. Would he enjoin ſuch ſpecial Officers, ſo miraculouſly qualified and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:102539:17"/> owned, to inform us of, prepare us for, and comfort us with ſo great a Bleſſing, and to repreſent it to us as the alluring and refreſhing aggravation of that State to come, <hi>that we ſhould be with Chriſt for ever?</hi> Did they preach falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood by ſpecial Order, and with ſuch Atteſtations to their Meſſage, and ſuch aſſiſtance in their Enterprize from the God of Truth, and from his eminently faithful and true Witneſſes? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> xi. 2. Why is this ſtatedly to influence all our practical Chriſtianity, if no ſuch Matter be deſigned for us? <hi>Joh.</hi> xii. 26. <hi>Tit.</hi> ii. 12, 14. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> iii. 14. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> v. 9. Our preſſing Pleas and Motives that are to animate and enforce our Duties, Sufferings, and Conſolations, with all thoſe exerciſed Graces which are to ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſuch Performances, Submiſſions, and dutiful Rejoicings by the way, do evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently bear themſelves upon this Hope, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> i. 5-11. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> ii. 13-17. <hi>Heb.</hi> x. 32-37. How copiouſly and ſtrongly might I improve theſe Scriptural Hints to prove this comfortable Truth, had I
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102539:18"/> but a better Head and Heart! But (to conclude this Demonſtration) laſtly; How could the Son of God himſelf ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that Glory and Delight which he ſo reckons on, in the ſucceſs of what he undertook, were not his purchaſed and redeemed Ones to be with him? <hi>John</hi> xvii. 22, 24. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> i. 10, 12. We find that <hi>Chriſt and his muſt go together in unto the Marriage,</hi> Mat. xxv. 10. And what is this going in together, but the joint entrance and admiſſion of Head and Members into that State of Royal Entertainments within the Vail? Would Chriſt have begg'd of God, both the diſcovery and impartment of his Glory to his Members, had not both theſe been highly valued by him? <hi>Joh.</hi> xvii. 22, 24. Will not Chriſt (think we) count it his Honour, to have his own produced in open Court as Signs and Wonders? <hi>Heb.</hi> ii. 13. to bring his Sons to Glory? <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. and to have that Church for which he gave himſelf, and which he loved ſo dearly, preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to himſelf a glorious Church, not
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:102539:18"/> having ſpot or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing; but holy and without blemiſh? <hi>Epheſ.</hi> v. 25-27. And to ſee us fixed in his own Preſence, as the eternal ſtately Monuments of his magnificent and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious Grace &amp; Love? What was the Plea wherewith he accented his dying Prayer for his, that God would charge his ſpecial Providence with them, but this, <hi>that I am glorified in them?</hi> John xvii. 10. And will the Head be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by being eternally parted from his Members? Where lies the Glory of a Teacher, but in the Wiſdom of his Scholars? and could Chriſt be glorified in making his expert in the Doctrine of Lies and Forgeries? What! bring Men to diſcern and credit &amp; rely upon what only was deluſive! How can we learn this as a <hi>Truth</hi> in Jeſus, <hi>that we ſhall live with him for ever,</hi> when no ſuch thing ſhall come to paſs? <hi>I have told you—that when it comes to paſs, ye might believe,</hi> Joh. xiv. 29. The Signs which God gave of a falſe Prophet under the Law, were either ſpeaking what was
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:102539:19"/> abſolutely falſe; or Truth, to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance Irreligion or Idolatry. And can either of theſe be charged on Chriſt, and judged to be his Glory? Wherein conſiſts the Glory of a Prieſt, but in the acceptance and ſucceſs of what he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly offereth to the determined Ends thereof? And can Chriſt our great High Prieſt be glorified as a Prieſt for ever, whoſe Sacerdotal Faithfulneſs could never bring up thoſe unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in Heaven, for whom, and to which End he did declaredly offer up himſelf? <hi>Heb.</hi> ix. 12, 15, 24, 28. And wherein is Chriſt glorified as a King, if his Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Subjects muſt not abide with him for ever? <hi>John</hi> xv. 10, 11. <hi>Heb.</hi> v. 9. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> iv. 6, 8. When he delivereth up the Kingdom to the Father, hath he no Subjects to produce, fitted unto the Felicities and Employments of his own Glorious Preſence? And can he be glorified that hath no Subjects to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore him for his governing them ſo well? And how can he be glorified as the Captain of the Hoſts of God in the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:102539:19"/> great War with Satan, if he muſt ſit in Heaven alone, and have no victorious Followers to produce and ſhew there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as proofs of his heroick, skilful, faithful Conduct and Atchievements? 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> iii. 8. <hi>Rom.</hi> viii. 18, 35-39. And how can Chriſt be glorified in and by his Saints, unleſs they ſee what God hath done for him, and in what Royal State he ſits, inhabiting the Praiſes, and (perhaps) ordering the Affairs, and darting forth that Glory which muſt diffuſe it ſelf through all the Regions and Inhabitants of that bleſſed World above? He muſt be glorified and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at, and will be ſo when we are brought to ſee his Face, to bear his I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, to ſhare in the Viſions, Services, and Fruitions of that State, all which ſhall to the Life expreſs his Intereſt in God's Heart, and ours in his Heart; and what a Friend God is to him, and he to us: So that with Chriſt we are ſure to be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:102539:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>III.</hi> The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs of this Paſſage.</head>
               <p n="1">1. O what Attractives have we to a Heavenly Mind and Life! Chriſt and a Kingdom with him! Who would not breath and ſtrive to reach that bleſſed State? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.8, 9. O let that Paſſage in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.58. be well conſidered, concocted, and digeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by you, ſo as to make you every way greatly conformable thereto: and let not Head, Inheritance and Hearts be parted. Did not <hi>Paul</hi> bear this Truth upon his Heart, and court us all to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him in the heavenlineſs of his Mind and Life? <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.14, 15. So love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is the Lord of Glory, and ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently doth the great God tranſmit his Glory even through the Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of our glorified Redemer, as that the Comforts of the Heavenly State will be exceedingly abated, were not his glorious Preſence there. And when he comes from Heaven to judg the World, the Hoſts and Citizens of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:102539:20"/> that bleſſed State will joyfully attend his motions, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.31.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If there be no Love to Chriſt, there would be no Joy in Heaven. Thoſe that have ſtumbl'd at his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, will be confounded at his Glory, <hi>Mark</hi> 8.34. to 38. The Crown of Life and Glory is reſerv'd for, and ſhall be only given to thoſe that are lovers of his Appearance. For who can think that the Glories of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly State, and the Pleaſures of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding Chriſt therein, can be <hi>their</hi> Portion, upon <hi>whom</hi> the great Sentence of <hi>Anathema Maranatha</hi> (i. e. curſed <hi>till the Lord come</hi>) is paſt? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.22. Heaven cannot countenance and reward Contempt of Chriſt. The Son of Righteouſneſs, Heaven's Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the Temple of that bliſsful State above, muſt either be the Heart's Delight, or Chriſt and Heaven can be no Portion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. No Chriſt! no Heaven. Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven muſt needs be loſt where Chriſt is
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:102539:21"/> miſs'd of, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.12. No Chriſt! no entrance into Glory: for Heaven is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>the Glory of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.14. Chriſt muſt be glorifi'd, if ever Heaven be reach'd. The Lord from Heaven is Lord of Heaven, <hi>Matth</hi> 28.18, 19. And he muſt be <hi>Crowned and own'd as Lord</hi> in Hearts, and as the only Holy One of God, by thoſe to whom he will give the Crown of Life. The Key of Heaven is in his Hand, and he will let in none but faithful Subjects. He cannot bear the preſence of the Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> there, nor hath he any Manſions for them: they are too contrary to his Holineſs, to have admiſſion into his Preſence. To let in rotten Hearts, would be to patronize and crown Rebellion. And is it meet that the Croſs, the Crown, and Glory of the Son of God ſhould ſerve the Devil? What! ſhall Chriſt proſtitute his Blood and Scepter unto the firſt-born of Apoſtacy and Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, or to the Seed thereof?</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:102539:21"/>4. Then Chriſt in Heaven ſhould be addreſs'd unto, to lift up Hearts and Perſons thither. Thus <hi>Stephen</hi> ſaw the Lord in Heaven, and begg'd his gracious help, and that not without ſucceſs, <hi>Act</hi> 7.55 to 59. It is not eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Arm, no nor any Arm but Chriſt's, that is fit to deal with ſuch dark heavy Souls as ours, ſo as to lift them up, and let them into Heaven, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12. <hi>Jude</hi> 24, 25. O then, deſponding Hearts, go make your moans to Chriſt, look up to him with your Hearts in your Eyes, and cry, <hi>Fain would I come to thee, but cannot; Jeſus thou Son of</hi> David <hi>help; and thou who ruleſt all things, if thou canst do any thing, who art the revealed Arm of God to bring great things to paſs, O have compaſſion on me, and raiſe up Heart and Soul and all to thee.</hi> Mark 9.22. Chriſt cry'd to God, as to one able to ſave from Death, <hi>and he was heard,</hi> Heb. 5.7. Cry you to Jeſus Chriſt, for he can ſave you to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. Lifts at the laſt and deadlieſt pinches, are the moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:102539:22"/> and endearing Lifts. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that a dying Chriſt once bare a Malefactor from the Croſs to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and bravely reſcu'd him from great deſtruction, and fixt him in his own Preſence; <hi>This day thou ſhalt be with me in Paradiſe.</hi> O it was a Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing won by Prayer, and that to Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.42, 43.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Then Heaven ſhould have no Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals if Chriſt be there: to be with Chriſt is far better, and that abandons all Compariſons, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23. Chriſt knew the pureſt Manſions where they were. Below they could not be, for Sin hath chang'd the Glory of all low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er things to ſhame and blackneſs: And little is there in them now, ſave Names and Shadows; and till theſe fly away, <hi>Chriſt, and our Life with him, is ſtill hid in God,</hi> Cant. 4.6. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.2 to 4. And ſhould not our Hearts then be gone to Heaven, and bound for thoſe moſt vaſt and glorious Regions, where our Dear Lord will keep his Reſidence for ever? What! Chriſt on
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:102539:22"/> his Throne, concerned, and preparing for gathering up all his Favorites to himſelf! and we not courted from a Dung-hill! all the World without one Chriſt is but a Trifle. No Chriſt, no worth in things; what Heart then for them! thoſe Joys, Relations, Gifts, Poſſeſſions and Accompliſhments are but vain and ſmall; nothing but dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Charms and Pageantries, whoſe Soul and Savour the Lord of Glory is not, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.7, 8. Prize things as they ſpeak Chriſt; for all the World with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him is not worth one Heart; there is neither Gain nor Glory in it.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Were Heaven poſſeſs'd by Chriſtleſs Hearts, yet would Content be wanting. Frowns from the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Feaſt would ſpoil the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Reliſhes of the Banquet. One, <hi>Friend, how cam'ſt thou in hither?</hi> would make men ſit at Table with little Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, and leſs Joy, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.12.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The Hopes of raiſed quickned Hearts are ſafe, and may be great. Chriſt, in the midſt of what we hope
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:102539:23"/> for, may and ſhould quiet all. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.19, 20. It's pity ſuch a Paſſage ſhould be paſs'd over without a conſiderate pauſe. Hath Chriſt broke through the Vail, and is he got within it, to leave our Souls without an Anchor of Hope, that may prove ſure and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt? Can Chriſt enter Heaven for us, and then forget his Work? Can the Fore-runner quite deſert thoſe lively and ſolicitous Members, that breath and ſtrive ſo much to trace and to tread his Steps after him? He that hath loſt his Blood below, what! hath he loſt his Heart above? ſurely our Head was never crown'd to ſhame his Members Hopes, and Joys. Our expectations of that State may be invigorated great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by this, <hi>That Chriſt our Hope is ſet upon his Throne therein. Chriſt is our bleſſed Hope,</hi> Tit. 2.13. <hi>According to our earneſt expectation and our hope in him, we cannot be aſham'd,</hi> Phil. 1.20 to 23. &amp; 3.20. It is <hi>by Chriſt that our Hope is laid up in Heaven,</hi> Col. 1.5. <hi>He makes the Promiſe ſure to all the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:102539:23"/> Seed,</hi> Rom. 5.10. Chriſt came from Heaven to be a Ranſom, and ſo he was, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.15. and he is in Heaven to plead his Wounds, and by his Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion to animate and ſucceed the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Claims and Expectations of all his Members, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.34, 35. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p then with Hearts and Hopes;</hi> and bid defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance unto all Diſcouragements. Chriſt by his entrance into Heaven, and by his poſſeſſing it, as our raiſed and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted Head, hath given one Lift; and ſurely then, his next lift will effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bear up all. Savoury, full, and pertinent is that both witty and weighty Paſſage in <hi>Tertullian de Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectione Carnis,</hi> cap. 51. <hi>Quemadmodum enim nobis Arrhabonem reliquit, ita &amp; à nobis Arrhabonem carnis accepit &amp; vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it in Caelum; pignus totius ſummae illuc quandoque redigendae ſecurae eſtote caro &amp; ſanguis. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpâſtis &amp; caelum &amp; reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Dei in Chriſto.</hi> The earneſt of the Spirit left, and the earneſt of Fleſh carri'd up to Heaven; a Pledg that all ſhall once be fetch'd up thither. The
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:102539:24"/> Kingdom of God, and Heaven poſſeſt in Chriſt, makes all ſecure. O then let Fleſh and Hearts, <hi>both reſt in hope;</hi> for Chriſt in Heaven will fetch us all to Heaven: for there at God's right Hand ſtands Chriſt to plead and vindicate, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.55. and there he ſits to hear, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe and rule; <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3, 13, 14. And if he fail in both, then may the lively Hopes (1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3.) of quickened Hearts (<hi>Eph.</hi> 2.5). expire and die. And if ſo, then where is our Anchor ſure and ſtedfaſt reaching to that within the Vail? Was not the Heart of our aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending Lord and Head exceeding mindfull of his Friends, and warm toward them? <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.17. and cool'd it by the way? <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.15. No ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, all that are truly and firmly Chriſt's, alway lie warm upon his Heart. Let him be where he will, though in the heights of all his Glory, he is yet <hi>our High Prieſt,</hi> Heb. 4.14. &amp; 8.1. <hi>Our Life,</hi> Col. 3.4. <hi>Our Head,</hi> Eph. 1.22, 23. <hi>Our Peace,</hi> Eph. 2.14. <hi>Our Hope,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.1. <hi>Our Lord,</hi> 1. Cor. 1.2. <hi>Our
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:102539:24"/> Saviour,</hi> Tit. 1.4. <hi>The Shepherd and Biſhop of our Souls,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.25. <hi>and our Advocate,</hi> 1 John 2.1. And can Chriſt in Heaven, <hi>ſtatedly and avouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly,</hi> under ſuch near and ſure and dear Relations to us, ſuffer our Hopes to fall? ſurely his Exaltation puts no pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod to his Relation to us, nor to thoſe Bowels that are proper to it; nor to thoſe Expectations that are built upon it. It's true, his Joys are high, his Truſt is great: but it is as true, that his Heart is commenſurate with and anſwers both: nor will his Kingdom pleaſe him without <hi>his</hi> Bride: he will ſtep once more from Heaven to fetch Her to Himſelf, <hi>John</hi> 14.3.</p>
               <p n="8">8. O what an Antidote is this Hope againſt the Snares and Fears of things below! 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. the Croſs is hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, and Hearts are ſoon unfixed; when Heaven, and Chriſt therein, and our determinate abode with him, are not our lively Hope and ſtated Poize. The Croſs can make no breach, while Chriſt in Heaven thus ſets his Heart upon us: and we have ſent our Hearts
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:102539:25"/> intirely after him, &amp; keep them there, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.34, 35. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34. And Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures can do but little hurt, whilſt this great Hope reliſhes duly with us. All the Delights of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Court could never reach the Heart of <hi>Moſes.</hi> When Chriſt and Heaven had got his Eye and fixt it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.25, 26. Hearts ſhould be under their reſtraint in law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Mirth, and at enmity with ſinful Mirth, during the abſence of their Lord, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.15. <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> grew careleſs of himſelf until his Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned in peace, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.24. No joy but in his Maſter's preſence: And ſhall not Chriſt in Heaven correct and moderate our Joys in things below? Groans to be ſtript of Earth, and Fleſh, and to be gone to Chriſt in Heaven ſhould be the deepeſt Groans. And truly, Sirs, if Chriſt in Heaven have not your Hearts, they will be prone to Surfeits or Diſtractions. You ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will be tunn'd with Wind, or drunk with Vanity, or wrack'd with Cares and Fears. Hearts pitcht on
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:102539:25"/> Chriſt in Heaven, know where to be full and welcom, when things below have ſhew'd their beſt, and done their worſt. They have a Glory that will pierce the darkeſt Cloud, and reach the greateſt Deep, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5. Their bittereſt Herbs, and ſharpeſt Agonies, may poſſibly be their entertainment at their laſt Paſſover: but theſe their ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liv'd Sorrows are but to uſher in, and aggravate their Maſter's Joys. Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures poſſeſt and kept by Chriſt for them, and to be poſſeſt by them in his own immediate Preſence, muſt needs be great. O Chriſtians, remember Heaven, and Chriſt therein; and what he is there preparing for you; and fear neither Plots, nor Strokes, nor Rumors, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4, to 7. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.10, to 12. Let your exalted Head, and this your elevating Hope, diſtil ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences upon your exercis'd Hearts, as to make you valiant for your Prize, exalted in your Aims, triumphant in your Hopes and Sufferings, and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more inſulting over the Cheats and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:102539:26"/> Dangers that attend you. He ſells his Head and Hopes for thirty Pieces, that is intangl'd with or unhing'd by any thing below this Head and Heritage, and theſe things above. Sure Chriſt in Heaven, ſo evidently intent upon your being brought to live where he is, wants neither Heart, nor Worth, nor Joys, to make you know and to acknowledg that he is a Non-ſuch Friend; and though rough-handed <hi>Eſau</hi> may be the firſt-born of your Entertainments here, yet <hi>Jacob</hi> hath him by the Heel, and ſhall ſupplant him. <hi>Suffer and reign,</hi> theſe are the terms of Life, the Royal Law of Hope, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. Ought not we (as well as Chriſt) to ſuffer and ſo to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into Glory? <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.26. with <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. Muſt not he follow Chriſt that deſigns to reach what he hath got? <hi>John.</hi> 12.26. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. What though the Way be foul and rugged? What ſhould diſcourage you in thoſe Paths, where every ſtep you take is an advance toward Chriſt in Heaven?
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:102539:26"/> Your Faith in Chriſt, and Hope of Heaven, are as the Dawnings of this Day to you: and every look at Chriſt in Glory, is as a Lift toward Heaven, and as a Foretaſt of it. A look at Chriſt in Glory bore up the Spirit of that Proto-martyr <hi>Stephen</hi> above the debaſements which carnal Fears pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce in others, and would otherwiſe have brought him under.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Why ſhould not Things above make us remember and ſend our Hearts to Chriſt above? had not Chriſt bought the Prize of Heaven, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.11, 14. and made our way thereto, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.19, 20. and peirced the Vail, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.8. and won and worn the Crown, through his own Blood, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. our being with our Lord in Glory had been beyond our reach and hope, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3, 4. An open Heaven for us coſt Chriſt a wounded Heart. He <hi>was poor to make us rich,</hi> 2 Cor. 8.9. Our ſprings of Hopes and Joys came from this cloven <hi>Lehi</hi> (if I may allude to <hi>Judg.</hi> 15.19.) where the Spring that God clave was
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:102539:27"/> not in the Jaw-bone, but in the place called <hi>Lehi,</hi> becauſe of the miraculous execution that was done by the <hi>Jaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone</hi> of an Aſs,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Maxilla.</note> (as <hi>Lehi</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifies); and ſhould not Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in hopes inthrone our Lord in Heart? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. It was this made the Apoſtle's Heart ſo warm and active; <hi>Wherefore we labour,</hi> &amp;c. Verſ. 9. <hi>Good-Will</hi> indeed <hi>toward Men,</hi> when ſuch good things were purchaſt for them, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.14. O then Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, if there be either Worth or Love, Bowels or Bounty in that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly State, ſo aggravated by our there <hi>ever being with the Lord,</hi> let all your Hearts be evermore for Chriſt. He walk'd in the <hi>Valley of the Shadow of Death, that you might fear no evil,</hi> and felt the Pangs and Strokes of Death, with all the loads and bitterneſs thereof conſiſtent with the dignity, innocence, and deſigns of ſuch a Perſon, as the Son of God was, ingaged in ſuch Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatorial Work, and all purſuant to this great Deſign, <hi>That Life and Immortal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:102539:27"/> might be intail'd upon us,</hi> who our ſelves could not live till he himſelf had undergone and conquer'd Death. Nor would he bring us to himſelf, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch advantages, and upon ſuch terms as ſhould evidently and greatly miniſter to univerſal ſatisfaction and renown. So black was that thick Cloud wherein this Sun of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs did ſet and paſs into his glorious State, thus to prepare our way to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in Heaven, as that the ſight there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of made his awakened Soul to trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and to ſolicite God for help; <hi>Mark</hi> 14.34. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.8, 9. Yet through this Cloud he wrought his Way, to diffuſe his Glory through the Heavenly Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and to make the Hoſts and the Inhabitants thereof the amazed Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of his triumphant Grace and Faithfulneſs: And thence to afford thoſe Influences which ſhould prepare us for, and ſuit us to that State. Bleſſed is Heaven that Chriſt is in it, and bleſſed are holy Hearts below that Chriſt in Heaven is theirs, and for
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:102539:28"/> them. Chriſt there inthron'd, and imploy'd for us, ſhould looſen all our Hearts from all ſave what his Heart is upon. His Work and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in that holy Place, hath both its Voice and Force. He ſpeaks not now to us in roaring Thunder-claps from the burning Mount; nor doth that <hi>Blood through which God brought him from the Dead,</hi> and conſecrated the High Prieſt of our Profeſſion to his moſt noble Work within the Vail, cry like the Blood of <hi>Abel</hi> for Revenges, to fill our Hearts with Enmity or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh; but it is an alluring grateful Whiſper from betwixt the Cherubims of Grace and Glory; a Call to <hi>Piſgah</hi> thence to behold <hi>Emanuel</hi>'s Land, that promiſed and expected State of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Joy: hence therefore let us ſend our Hearts to Chriſt as a poor Widow's Mite, only to acknowledg our Obligations to him, and to teſtify how much we love our Lord and Head. And, O thou Prince of Life and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, thou Oracle of Truth, the ſealed
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:102539:28"/> 
                  <hi>Amen</hi> of all God's Promiſes, and of our glorious Expectations; thou Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror of Graves, of Hearts, and Hell; whom to behold is our great Hope and Joy, (for without Thee, the Prince of Life, we cannot live, and never look to know what it is indeed to live till we be got to Thee). Lend us a Beam of Light to view thee by; that every Look may melt our Hearts, and make them ſhine and burn. That thus our Admirations and Affections may bear ſome ſmall proportion to their Object, and more effectually ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure us from loſing Hearts below, and throwing them away upon unworthy things. We loſe Affections in miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken worth; and thou get'ſt little elſe hereby but Slights and Stabs, and all becauſe we know not Thee the Lord of Glory. How little is thy Love admir'd by us, becauſe we feel it not! how little are we affected with thee, becauſe we have not ſeen thee! how little do we bemoan our abſence from thee, becauſe we are ſo little appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:102539:29"/> of what thy glorious Preſence ſo liberally produces and diſpenſes! how eaſily are we courted and prevail'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to forget thee, becauſe we do ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle think upon, and are ſo little affected with thy Wounds below, and thy Worth and Joys above? Eyes have not ſeen, Hearts cannot love. O lift, and help, and warm, and fix, and conquer all. O let our Hearts be made as faſt and pure as Heaven. Let preparations be compleat in Hearts, as well as in thoſe Manſions of eternal Glory with thy ſelf, which thou haſt order'd and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courag'd us to expect. O let not Grace and Love, as large as Heaven, be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our Feet any more, but upon our Hearts. Could ever Heaven be ours, or found and valu'd by us as Heaven indeed, without thy Sufferings, Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, Grace and Preſence? And can we think on Heaven indeed, and yet forget the Throne of Majeſty and Grace that is there, and him that ſits thereon, acting purſuantly to this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful Hope, that we ſhall ſee him
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:102539:29"/> in his Meridian Glory, and be with him for ever?</p>
               <p n="10">10. Let nothing have or influence your Hearts below, but that which ſuits the Heart of Chriſt above. All muſt be like the Lord that are to live with him; <hi>and he that hath this Hope in him, muſt purify himſelf as Chriſt is pure,</hi> 1 Joh. 3.2, 3. Whatever Chriſt died to ſtart below, he lives above to propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, to vindicate, and compleat. He hath as true a Heart for Godlineſs now as ever: and he was call'd the <hi>Holy Child</hi> after his Exaltation, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.27. Chriſt's Heart is pure, ſo are his Joys; for they are the Joys of Holineſs in its utmoſt luſter, vigour, and extent. You muſt be pure, or Chriſt and you muſt part; the Conſtitution of the heavenly State admits of no diſorder. His holy Soul abhors what ſeems to ſhake his Father's Throne. He can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bear it, that a filthy Soul ſhould ſtand before him, for <hi>God's Name is in him,</hi> Exod. 23.21. <hi>In that he lives, he lives to God,</hi> Rom. 6.10. He dy'd
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:102539:30"/> with Holineſs upon his Heart; and as a Martyr for it, as well as to make an atonement for us, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.22, 23. With a pure Heart he went to Heaven; and can you think that Purity can waſt and rot, when fac'd with the moſt immediate Viſions of God, and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd with all things moſt expreſſive of God's complacency in it? Surely God's greateſt Favours muſt bear the cleareſt Characters and Signatures of his eſſential Purity and Holineſs. Hath Holineſs loſt its Intereſt in Heaven, ſince Chriſt went thither? Or hath Sin gotten ground by Chriſt's aſcent to Glory? O Sinners, be no longer doting Fools, and ſtupid Sots. Lay by your Venom, and <hi>cleanſe your Hearts and Hands,</hi> Jam. 4.8. 1 Cor. 6.9, to 11. The <hi>Heart,</hi> the <hi>Blood,</hi> the <hi>Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance,</hi> the <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Triumphs</hi> of our Lord are all engag'd to revive Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the World, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.4. Dote not upon deceitful Riches; <hi>Chriſt is the Pearl of Price, by whom you are to be inrich'd in every thing.</hi> Let not the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:102539:30"/> Mammon of Unrighteouſneſs uſurp the Throne of Chriſt, the over-valued World is a perfect Enemy to Chriſt, to Heaven and Heavenlineſs. Be not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed nor over-charg'd with Cares, be not intangl'd whilſt you are allow'd to be imploy'd. Take heed of <hi>Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laes,</hi> leſt you loſe your Locks, and be bereav'd of your Chriſtian Strength and Hopes. Fear not the Frowns, prize not the Smiles of Mortal Duſt beyond Divine Allowance. Chriſt hates Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitors; Chriſt did it not below, he loves it not above. Be not buri'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live in Sloth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.11. there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in Heaven but Life and Joy in full conformity to all the Laws and Purpoſes of that compleat Theocracy. Diligence brings in rich Delights; 'tis Sloth that makes Hell ſo full, and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſo empty. Be not high-minded, neither court nor cheriſh Self in any dreſs by Pride and Rage. <hi>Haman</hi>'s pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment made him but high enough to reach a Halter. Learn of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29. Heaven could not bear the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:102539:31"/> Pride of Angels, no more can Chriſt endure the Pride of Man. Pleaſe not your ſelves, or others, till you have anſwer'd all your Maſter's Claims, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.1, 2, 3. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.10. Be knit to nothing but to your Lord in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; for why ſhould he be made an Underling or Cipher here below? Chriſt ours in Heaven! a better Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and Inheritance than States and Kingdoms here. Be more ſollicitous about the temper, tendency, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine Iſſues of your Hearts and Ways, than about the Events of Providence, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.9, 10. Your beſt Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are with Chriſt; if they ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, you cannot loſe Treaſures above, and your exalted Head in <hi>Bonds,</hi> in <hi>Power,</hi> and in <hi>Poſſeſſion</hi> to ſecure them, ſpeak you too ſafe and rich to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done. Be ſilent Proſtrates at the foot of Chriſt; if his preſence be your Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, he muſt needs be much above you every way: therefore obſerve the Words, the Looks, the Steps of Chriſt, and let them rule you: And let his
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:102539:31"/> Diſpenſations here below be all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd by you, and reſted in. Chriſt is in Heaven about your Work; and that he be pleaſed by you, doth moſt concern you, and beſt become you. And when you come to be with him for ever, how deeply and quickly will he make you ſenſible of that great Wiſdom, wonderful Grace, and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Power, which brought you ſafely to himſelf in Glory.</p>
               <p n="11">11. And O what a Figure will Chriſt then make in Heaven, when that State is compleatly filled, and when he hath gathered all his Family up to Glory? 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11. If in thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratory Scenes of Providence where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Redeemer addreſt himſelf to Action, and began his glorious At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievements, and was priviledged to open the Sealed Book, there were ſuch Acclamations, and ſolemn Congratulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this his peculiar Priviledg &amp; Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative by all in Heaven &amp; Earth; and if there were ſuch proſtrate Venerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of him, as we find in <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.8-11. &amp; 5.9-14. and this conjunctly with
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:102539:32"/> his Father: How will his Name and Glory be aggrandized when all his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorites ſhall be with him? All the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of Godlineſs relate to Chriſt, and have their undoubted Aggravati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from him, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. and how wondrouſly glorious hath God repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented him to us below? <hi>Col.</hi> 1.15-19. &amp; 2.2, 3, 9, 10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2-13. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5, 6. <hi>John</hi> 14.6. And if theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, theſe earthly things; [theſe ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowings forth of Chriſt and of his Kingdom to us, even by Schemes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated to our Capacities in this our dark and diſtant State] be looked upon as ſcarcely to be credited by Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and yet ſo wonderful in the Eyes of the diſcerning Chriſtian: What would the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> be then thought to be, were they diſcovered to us in words more ſuited to their Excellency, than to our Capacity? <hi>John</hi> 3.12. with 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.23, 24. &amp; 2.9-14. &amp; 2.12, 2-4. We find great notices taken of him by the Heavenly State whilſt in this outward Court,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:102539:32"/> miniſtring in the Port and poſture of a Servant: For as the Spirit of Prophecy foretold him, Types repreſented him, and the Word of Promiſe entitled us to the hopes and benefits of his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, and propitious Mediation: So the Spirit forms his Body, Angels declare his Birth, Miracles atteſt his Dignity, Doctrines, and Authority, and Ability to form us for, and bring us to Himſelf. Nature obeys him, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils fly before him, <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> talk with him; Souls come in by Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes, and value nothing like his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Conduct, Government, and Grace. God owns him as <hi>his Son,</hi> as his <hi>Royal Oracle</hi> and <hi>Agent,</hi> by a Voice from Heaven, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.16-21. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.6-12. and all the Inſtitutions and Tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Kingdom of God amongſt Men, muſt have the Name of Chriſt enſtamp'd upon them. And when Chriſt had finiſhed his Courſe, and Work below, God raiſes him from the Dead, and ſhews him openly; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands the Angels to worſhip him, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:102539:33"/> to report his Reſurrection: makes this the great Baſe and Pillar of his Goſpel-Kingdom; carries him up to Heaven, many hundreds of credible Witneſſes beholding his Aſcenſion; and ſets him at his own right Hand, putting the Reigns of all Government into his Hands. And then the Father ſends the Holy Spirit, in the <hi>Son's Name,</hi> to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify him, (as Chriſt had ſaid before, <hi>John</hi> 16.13-15.) to ſeal this Truth, to enable Perſons to declare and prove it, and to make the Goſpel proſperous in its great Deſign. But as to Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he in the heavenly <hi>Places</hi> and <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs</hi> (for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> imports both) <hi>ſits far above all Principality, Power, Might, Dominion, and every Name that is named in—even the World to come, having all things under his Feet; becauſe he is given as Head over all things to his Church, which is his Body, the fulneſs of him that filleth all in all,</hi> Epheſ. 1.20-23. Hence <hi>the whole Family in Heaven and Earth is named of him,</hi> Eph. 3.15. The Church
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:102539:33"/> in the compleatneſs of its Triumphant State, is called <hi>his Everlaſting King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.11. And <hi>when he ſhall have put down all Rule, Authority and Power, he will deliver up the Kingdom to the Father,</hi> as a fit Preſent to the Majeſty of Heaven, as a clear Proof and Monument of his own Mediato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Faithfulneſs, and as fit Subjects of his own Paternal Government and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, or as his acquired Inheritance to poſſeſs for ever, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24-28. For who can any way imagine, that the delivery of theſe Subjects to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall be the depoſing of the Son from his triumphant Government, that well conſiders Chriſt as placed by God <hi>upon the ſame Throne with himſelf?</hi> Rev. 3.21. Is not Chriſt ſaid <hi>to reign for ever and ever?</hi> Rev. 11.15. O what a Pleonaſm (or fulneſs of expreſſion) is there in that paſſage! <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.21. It is a Doxology richly phraſed, and that (as in the Greek, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) whereto I never yet read or heard of any Parallel in any
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:102539:34"/> Greek Author. See alſo 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. ſo vaſt is the reach of the inſpiring Spirit, ſo deep the Thoughts, ſo full the Heart of the inſpired Pen-man; becauſe ſo great the Dignity and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives of our enthroned and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Redeemer in this his Day and Kingdom. What Eye ſo ſharp and ſtrong on Earth, as to comprehend, or tolerably to reach the ſenſe of that great Paſſage, in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.14.16 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Timothy</hi> is charged to keep the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mandment—<hi>till the appearing of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> (mind now what follows) <hi>which in his Times he ſhall ſhew, who is the bleſſed and only Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords; who only hath Immortality, dwelling in Light, which no Man can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach unto, whom no Man hath ſeen, nor can ſee; to whom is</hi> (as well as <hi>be) Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Power everlaſting? Amen.</hi> And here, O that my <hi>heart</hi> was equal to wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> poor purblind I diſcern in this great Paſſage, as ſhewing what notice muſt and will be taken of Jeſus Chriſt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:102539:34"/> For tho all theſe Attributions be made to God the Father, yet will this glorious Name appear exceedingly in the Revelation of the Son from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, who is ſaid to come in the Glory of his Father, <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.26. And we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not think his Heavenly Glory to be leſs than what attends him on his Throne of Judgment. And when all Eyes ſhall ſee him upon his Throne in Heaven; what Wonders ſhall we then behold! the cleareſt Mirrour, and moſt genuine Image of the Inviſible God, ſhedding abroad his Glory throughout that perfect World; and by the viſible Luſter of his Eminencies, the bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Diſpenſations of his Love, and the moſt accurate Government of his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Family and Kingdom, will he manifeſt <hi>his Intereſt</hi> in God, and <hi>our Intereſt</hi> in him, to be ſo great and grateful to the whole Society, as to command and gain all Hearts, Eyes, Services and Doxologies.</p>
               <p n="12">12. O what a Prize have we to make improvement of? What! live
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:102539:35"/> with Chriſt for ever! and then with ſuch Solemnities be caught up to him to meet him in the Air, ſo as to go away with him to Glory, and to part no more! Is ſuch a Truth and State only to exerciſe our ſpeculative Searches, to entertain our wanton Fancies, to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to diſcurſive Entertainments and bold Diſputes; or only by ſome politick Pretences thereunto, to ſerve our Carnal Intereſts thereupon! Think we that Chriſt, in his Deſcent from Heaven, his Return thither, his Exaltation there, or his determined and declared Purpoſe to enſtate us with himſelf therein, only intended that we ſhould trifle with ſuch Matters, or make them Engines for our ambitious and ſelfiſh Aims and Purpoſes? No greater prophanation and abuſe of ſuch a <hi>State,</hi> and <hi>Hope,</hi> and <hi>Friend in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> than this, that Chriſt himſelf ſhould be diſhonoured, and his great Aim and End concerning us neglected and defeated, by an ill Temper and Behaviour in and from us. Hence then
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:102539:35"/> ſuffer a word of Exhortation, and that to theſe following things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Clear up your Notions of this State and Hope; know with whom and where you are to be, and to what Purpoſes, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.1-4. You are to be with Chriſt in his Eternal Kingdom, there to behold his Glory, in all the Heights and Accuracies of full confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to him, that even there your rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and compleated Beings may ſerve the Purpoſes, and reap the Comforts of your Stations there. <hi>God's Houſhold is called a Building fitly framed together, here growing up</hi> (and there grown up) <hi>to be an holy Temple in the Lord; and all are built together for an Habitation of God through the Spirit,</hi> Epheſ. 2.21, 22. And theſe <hi>Epheſians</hi> (as others are) were to be filled <hi>unto</hi> all the Fulneſs of God; [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.19. And what doth this inſinuate? The uſe and luſter of the whole Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is not to be confined and aſcribed unto every Part. Nor are all the Parts to be in every thing alike; it is rather
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:102539:36"/> Symmetry and Harmony, than Iden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity or Equality, wherein the beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of that Building lies. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, variety of Parts, well laid and kept together, ſhews greatly the Skill and Wiſdom of the Architect. God himſelf only knows what vaſt Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Inhabitants that State con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains; <hi>Ten thouſand times ten thouſand, and thouſands of thouſands,</hi> Rev. 5.11. and, <hi>a thouſand thouſands miniſtred to him; and ten thouſand times ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſtood before him.</hi> Dan. 7.10. And theſe vaſt Multitudes are all digeſted into their ſeveral proper Ranks and Orders. Hence, <hi>Thrones, Dominions, Principalities, Powers,</hi> Coloſ. 1.16. <hi>Might,</hi> and <hi>Names named in the World to come,</hi> Epheſ. 1.21. And the faln Angels are ſaid to have left their <hi>Principality,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Jude 6. Thus Chriſt aſſigns Authority in his Day; to ſome, <hi>over ten,</hi> to others, <hi>over five Cities,</hi> Luk. 19.17-19. <hi>There is</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>one glory of the Sun, another of the Moon, another Glory of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:102539:36"/> the Stars, which themſelves alſo in their Glory, differ each from other. So alſo is the Reſurrection of the Dead,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.41, 42. And will not theſe be placed and uſed according to their dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent degrees in Glory, in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God and of Chriſt? It ſeems very improbable to me, <hi>(pace aliorum)</hi> that all in Heaven are equal in their Capacities, Stations, and Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; <hi>this only</hi> Obiter; <hi>and with all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to farther Diſcoveries and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Judgments,</hi> But that which is main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aimed at from the Apoſtle's hint, <hi>[unto all the fulneſs]</hi> is this, that we are here to <hi>grow up to all the Fulneſs of God,</hi> viz. to that degree of proficiency, and at laſt Perfection, which may beſt fill up and anſwer our fixed Place and Station in the living Temple of the great God. And then accordingly will God place and uſe us in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Kingdom; whereinto, according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we are minded of <hi>an abundant En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.11. But <hi>to the main Concern.</hi> Think not that Chriſt will
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:102539:37"/> bring you to himſelf, to give you ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Entertainments, or to exempt you from all further ſervice to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and himſelf; or to feed and ſatisfy an arrogant and revengeful Temper in you, as if the Satisfactions and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancements of that State only were to make you contemptuouſly to inſult over thoſe Enemies of yours who had vex'd or wronged you in the Fleſh. Nor are you there only to ſit ſtill, and gaze at the beautiful Objects of that State; nor only to ſing your vocal <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelujah's;</hi> nor only to entertain the Majeſty of the great <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and the viſible Beauty of that World, <hi>the Man Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> with Commendations and Applauſes, as if your Oral Panegyricks could be your delight; for the higheſt flights of Speech are low, the moſt maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culine vigour of Expreſſion is but flat and languid; and the moſt intimate In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpections, and vaſteſt reaches of created Intellects, are but ſhort and narrow as to the Objects of your Praiſe and Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the Heavens, <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.5. <hi>Job</hi> 11.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:102539:37"/> 7-9. 'Tis true, Chriſt Jeſus <hi>is the Image of the inviſible God;</hi> and the Glory of the Divine Nature (perſonally or <hi>bodily</hi> dwelling in him in its Fulneſs, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.9.) muſt ſuit its Emanations and Tranſmiſſions through the humane Nature, (and all its diſcoveries other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of it ſelf) unto the Capacities and Concerns of that moſt excellent Society above; which yet, as Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures have their Bounds, (for no Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can be infinite that is created). Whence we may eaſily infer, as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, an infinite <hi>reſidue</hi> of Perfection, (if I may call it ſo) which never can be known by any meer Creature. And it is more than I can prove, that God neither hath made, nor can make a ſort of Beings, to whom he doth, or will, or may diſcover himſelf by a Name higher, and clothed with more lofty Attributions, than either we, or thoſe Spirits above (called <hi>Angels,</hi> from their Miniſtrations to this World) can reach, or are capacitated for. But, <hi>De Deo vel vera dicere periculoſum.</hi> I dread to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:102539:38"/> walk in the impoſſible or forbidden ſearches of the incomprehenſible Sourſe and Abyſs of Perfection, leſt I ſhould meet with that <hi>ſevere and awful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primand, Who is this that darkens Counſel by Words without Knowledg?</hi> Job 38.2. But this may ſhew how lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle our Words or Thoughts can reach God's own eſſential Perfection. Yet is this Godhead united to <hi>the Man Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> But how, I ſolemnly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs I know not, though I believe it to be true, and think it eaſily demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble from Sacred Writ: And I think it as copiouſly aſſerted, and plainly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, as almoſt any Article of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith; and I take the Goſpel to have very little Myſtery comparative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if ſo far diluted as to loſe this cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tral Myſtery, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. And hence it plainly follows, that <hi>to be with the Lord,</hi> is a great aggravation of the Glory and Delightfulneſs of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly State, it being not improbable to me that Chriſt himſelf will be the Mediator of <hi>Fruition,</hi> as he hath been
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:102539:38"/> of Acquiſition. And therefore to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed; we cannot think, that <hi>to be with Chriſt</hi> infers a Peerage with him, or Partnerſhip in his Divine Excellencies and Prerogatives, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21. We are to <hi>worſhip him,</hi> and not to <hi>be worſhipped with him,</hi> Rev. 5.13. Phil. 2.10, 11. John 5.12, 13. What is Worſhip, but, <hi>Obſequium alicui praeſtitum propter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellentiam?</hi> A reverent acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Excellence, and fit Reſpects and Homage paid thereto? And if then Chriſt the Mediator be <hi>God-Man,</hi> hath he not <hi>therein</hi> the preeminence above all other Creatures in the Univerſe? and the Reſpects which muſt be paid thereto, what Worſhip will you call it? Names are to be ſuited unto things, they cannot otherwiſe duly repreſent them. Chriſt then as Mediator is more excellent than any meer Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, therefore as a middle Perſon to be more regarded: And what then will you call this <hi>over-plus of Reſpects?</hi> (if I may call it ſo) I know we may <hi>diſtinguiſh,</hi> where we cannot <hi>divide;</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:102539:39"/> and whether <hi>Divine Worſhip</hi> may fitly be diſtinguiſhed upon or not, I leave to the more accurate to determine. But I conceive that God expects, that the Humane Nature, <hi>as individuated in that exalted Perſon Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> ſhall have ſuch Honour paid thereto, as none beſides, in Heaven or Earth, ſhall be allowed to have. In a word, Chriſt <hi>as Mediator,</hi> is not <hi>ſo great as God,</hi> therefore the Worſhip muſt not riſe ſo high: Yet, <hi>as Mediator,</hi> he is above all Creatures, and more than they to be reſpected. Conſider well <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3-6. As <hi>Man</hi> there is Humane Excellence in its Height; as <hi>God,</hi> there is increated Excellence: As <hi>Mediator,</hi> there is a <hi>ſitting at God's right Hand:</hi> and he that ſits there, muſt and will be according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledged, and had in reverence by all in Heaven. And now let us ſee a little what that State imports, that we may form right Notions of it. And here we will, 1. Premiſe the Excellence of <hi>the Place,</hi> as ſuited to all the Grandieurs of the State, <hi>Epheſ.</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:102539:39"/> 4.10. the Inheritance of the Saints <hi>in Light,</hi> Col. 1.12. the <hi>Building made by God,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.1. Heb. 11.10, 16. &amp; 13.14. Joh. 14.2. But where and how 'tis ſituated, divided and accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, no <hi>Piſgah</hi> high enough on Earth for us to ſee it from, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.9-23. &amp; 22.1-5. And, 2. the Perfections of the <hi>Subjects</hi> to make them receptive of that State. Defecated Souls, and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Bodies, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.3. &amp; 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.3. with 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.50-54. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.14. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 14.14-17. For none muſt go with Chriſt to Glory, nor live with him for ever, whoſe Hearts and Lives are not for him whilſt here; and whoſe Spirits are not transform'd, and ſo adapted or ſuited to the Privileges and Miniſtrations of the Heavenly Kingdom, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.27. And therefore 'tis ſuppoſed and concluded, that the Conſtitution of the Soul be ſound and ſweet, and fit for its imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate entrance into Heaven, and its a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode with Chriſt for ever, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9-11. The Spirit of Chriſt imprinciples,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:102539:40"/> Providence exerciſes all theſe heavenly Principles; our Covenant-ſtate obliges us to the moſt lively exerciſe thereof: Habits are fix'd and ſtrengthned by Acts; and the Soul's firſt immediate look at Chriſt, compleats its Transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; and then is it admitted into the preſence of its Lord. So that in ſtrictneſs of Thoughts and Speech, the Temper of the Perſon muſt be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd from his State, as that which qualifies him for his admiſſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into. And then as to the Body, it muſt not <hi>be Fleſh and Blood,</hi> for that will be too weak and groſs for Chriſt his ſo glorious and majeſtick Preſence, and for the Viſions and Employments of the State above. <hi>Saul</hi> could not bear the Glory of Chriſt's perſonal Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to him, without aſtoniſhment and blindneſs, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.3-12. And in his Extaſy he knew not where and what he was, embodied or not, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.2, 3. And the appearance of an Angel made others as dead Men, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.2-4. And the Royal and Great Prophet, when he
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:102539:40"/> ſaw <hi>his Glory,</hi> cried out, <hi>Wo is me, I am undone,</hi> Iſa. 6.5. with <hi>John</hi> 12.41. How ſtrangely did Chriſt's Transfigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration confound <hi>Peter, James,</hi> and <hi>John?</hi> Mark 9.2-6. So that the Body muſt it ſelf be changed, in order to its meeting and being with the Lord, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.52, 53. Theſe things are then to be diſtinguiſhed from the State it ſelf, as needful Preparations for it. Now therefore to the State it ſelf; and here I ſhall avoid all fond Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Conjectures, and ſpeak hereof as God ſhall enable me, and doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct me. This State muſt then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude theſe things: (and how much more I know not.) 1. The Viſions of the Glory of our Lord; or, <hi>beholding Chriſt in all his Glory:</hi> And ſo our <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing where he is,</hi> Joh. 17.24. and that, not <hi>to aſtoniſhment and conſternation,</hi> but <hi>to delightful admiration,</hi> John 16.22. Jude 24. And here both Mind and Body have their looks at Chriſt to feaſt them both for ever. The ſymmetry and delicate Proportions of his Humane
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:102539:41"/> Body, the Beauty of his Face, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of his Countenance, the Pleaſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Speech, the placid Aſpects of his ſmiling Looks at us, the Glory of his Throne, the orderly Diſpoſals, Attendances, and Miniſtrations of all his Favorites and Attendants; with all the awful and yet delightful decencies of his Geſtures and Deportments to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all with him, and the Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Divinity in all this. O what an ocular Entertainment will this amount unto! What ſhall our Souls ſay then to all his evident Prerogatives, his wiſe Conduct, his excellent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, his bounteous Diſpenſations, his intimate Converſes with us, and the delight he evidently takes in the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and welfare of that State? And who knows what beſides? But this I now remember was touch'd upon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. 2. The glorious Benefits and Pleaſures that will reſult herefrom: There is <hi>Glory given,</hi> as well as <hi>Glory ſeen,</hi> John 17.22. called <hi>an Inheritance of the Saints in Light,</hi> Col. 1.12. the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:102539:41"/> 
                  <hi>Crown of Life,</hi> Jam. 1.12. A <hi>Kingdom prepared to be inherited,</hi> Mat. 25.34. The <hi>Joy of our Lord,</hi> ver. 21. <hi>Fulneſs of Joy and Pleaſures for evermore,</hi> Pſal. 16.11. We ſhall be honourable &amp; triumphing Members of the glorified Church in Heaven, and <hi>there</hi> and <hi>ſuch</hi> for ever; ſignalized with the Name <hi>of God,</hi> and of that perfected Corporation, and of our glorified Redeemer. Whether the Deity will (or can be) the Object of our immediate Viſion, I much doubt, and am prompted ſo to do, from 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17. &amp; 6.16. I only ſay, <hi>I doubt it much,</hi> but I cannot judg my ſelf infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible; but, <hi>when with Chriſt in Glory,</hi> our Knowledg of God will be more clear than now, and have more deep Impreſſions, and livelier Influences up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the whole Man than now it hath. <hi>We ſhall be like to Angels, being the Children of God, and of the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> Luk. 20.36. for then the Privileges and Prerogatives of our adopted raiſed State, will be in our actual and full Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion. We ſhall be ever under the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:102539:42"/> ſmiles of infinite Love, and under the moſt invigorating Influences of <hi>the God of Life;</hi> whoſe conſtant over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadowings of us ſhall draw forth all the vital Energies of our Faculties, (and perhaps of ſome Faculties which yet are latent in us, as being fitter for the Felicities and Employments of the <hi>End,</hi> than of the <hi>Way;</hi> which yet I rather offer than aſſert); and when exalted Faculties and Powers are pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced amongſt ſuch glorious Objects, in ſuch vaſt multitudes, and with ſuch great variety; when we converſe and dwell with Angels, ſo numerous, excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and endearing; when we have ſuch glorious Entertainments and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments with and for the Lord Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer; when we ſhall from himſelf receive immediately what he <hi>here</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and hath <hi>there</hi> prepared for us; the Fruits and Harveſt of all our Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, Labours, Prayers, and Hopes; when all our Dangers, Snares, Fears, Griefs and Maladies are gone; when all Chriſt's Enemies and ours are under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot;
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:102539:42"/> when the Divine Life, in its me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian Strength and Luſter, ſhews it ſelf; when all the Subjects of that State appear in their moſt accurate confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities unto their great Exemplar, <hi>each one as Chriſt reſembling the Children of a King,</hi> (as thoſe in a far lower ſenſe, <hi>Judg.</hi> 8.18.) <hi>Princes to look to,</hi> (as thoſe <hi>Ezek.</hi> 23.15. Not after the manner of the Babylonians, but) after the manner of the Sons of God: O what a State will this State be! To cloſe this Head: He that hath a genuine Idea, and right Notion of this State, muſt repreſent it to himſelf as that wherein Nature is perfected as to Things and Perſons, and fix'd in that Perfection; and Divine Government is compleated in all its Conſtitutions and Adminiſtrations; and all the Priviledges thereof diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, its Services perform'd exactly by all the Subjects thereof; and the great Ends and Purpoſes thereof attained and anſwered to univerſal ſatisfaction, and all this in the preſence of the Lord, upon his Throne, encompaſſed with
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:102539:43"/> his Redeemed Ones, who ſee his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, bear his Image, acknowledg his rich Grace and Love towards them, and ſerve and glorify his Name for ever, to his full ſatisfaction. God taking great delight in them, and they in him; and owning his Son before them all, as one that pleaſed his heart in bringing all theſe Sons to Glory, whilſt all theſe Morning Stars together ſing their Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelujahs with great harmony and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, and ſhout for joy, that God is <hi>all in all</hi> by Jeſus Chriſt with them; and that they can with ſo much order, chearfulneſs, and vigour, ſerve and pleaſe him moſt entirely and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully with his own in that Auguſt Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly; for the preſence of the Lord Redeemer there, reſembled, loved, and ſerved by all the Inheritors, Citizens, and Subjects of that State, with ſo much Wiſdom, Holineſs, and Vigour, ſpeaks Heaven indeed. But let me not run too far.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:102539:43"/>2. Comfort <hi>your ſelves,</hi> and <hi>one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother,</hi> with <hi>theſe words,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 4.18. Think ſeriouſly upon 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3-9. <hi>Put on the Breſt-plate of Faith and Love; and for an Helmet the Hope of Salvation. For God hath not appointed us to Wrath, but to obtain Salvation by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who died for us, that whether we wake or ſleep, we ſhould live together with him. Wherefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort your ſelves together, and edify one another, even as alſo ye do,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5. 8-11. The word here rendred <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is indeed, <hi>to play the Advocate,</hi> as the Matter ſhall require. To plead the Cauſe, the Ground and Uſefulneſs of this our glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Expectation, againſt diſcourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and afflictive Providences, as they are otherwiſe apt to diſpirit or diſturb us. When we are prone to ſwoon or tire, through the difficult Duties, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Burthens, ſmart Temptations, ſtrong Corruptions, and intricating poſtures of Affairs below: when we have little elſe in humane view, but
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:102539:44"/> great Work, and little Stength; huge Perplexities and ſtrange Intricacies in every Article of Concern, manifold Enemies and Hindrances aſſaulting us continually, and preſſing moſt ſeverely on us; and very little help or hope in view: O let us then our ſelves (and quicken one another to) repair unto <hi>this Hope as our beſt Refuge, and our moſt ſure and ſtedfaſt Anchor within the Vail, whither our</hi> Prodromus or <hi>Forerunner is for us entred,</hi> Heb. 6.18. Rom. 8.18. 2 Cor. 4. 16-18. uſing it as our richeſt Cordial, and urging it ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally and cloſely upon the Heart, until we are brought to our delightful and abſolute repoſe therein.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Comfort <hi>your ſelves</hi> with thoſe words, and ſo <hi>begin at Home,</hi> Rom. 5. 2. Phil. 3.3. For unleſs ſuch grateful words come from the Speaker's Heart unto the Hearers, from Principle to Principle, they are not likely to have ſuch invigorating Influences upon Souls, nor to have ſuch kindly Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Effects in Chriſtian Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:102539:44"/> as the Caſe requires. <hi>Vain talk</hi> about ſo great an Article of Hope, is dreadful: and it is no better as to him that ſpeaks about it, until his own Heart duly be affected with it. Great Notions, and high flights of Speech, are but as <hi>ſwelling Words of Vanity,</hi> to him whoſe Tongue is not attended and actuated with a transformed, and thereupon, concerned Soul. Nor can indeed the Speaker's End be right, whilſt his Heart is naught, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18. What God may do for the ſake of Truth, and with regard to his own Intereſt and Inſtitution, is one thing; and what ſuch an <hi>heartleſs Talker</hi> may expect, is another thing. And he that makes no reckoning of this bleſſed State and Hope himſelf, will not be very much concerned how ſuch things take with others, unleſs as it may ſerve thoſe lower Intereſts or popular Applauſes which are ſo much eyed and idolized by himſelf. But it is prophaneſs to the height, to proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute ſuch a <hi>Sacred Ordinance as Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:102539:45"/> Communion,</hi> and <hi>ſuch a glorious State and Hope,</hi> as being <hi>ever with the Lord,</hi> unto ſo mean and vile an End as ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate ſelfiſhneſs. O then make thorow work within, and be what all muſt be, <hi>that are to be for ever with the Lord.</hi> Your Directory in this Caſe, you have in <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11-14. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5-11. &amp; 3.11-14. and when that is done, then make this State your ſtated and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſional Conſolation and Refreſhment, that ſo you may comfort one another with the Comforts wherewith ye your ſelves are comforted of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.3-5. And what now is it, think you, to comfort your ſelves herewith? I will tell you, (as deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, labouring, and hoping, through your intreated Prayer for me, and the ſupply of the Spirit to me, thus to do) It is, 1. by cloſe and ſolemn contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, to repreſent this State unto your ſelves, (according to the Goſpel-Scheme or Figure) as <hi>great, ſure, near,</hi> and <hi>ſuited every way to make thoſe happy who obtain it;</hi> as <hi>yours,</hi> by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:102539:45"/> and in hope, (having been pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed, and being now poſſeſt <hi>by Chriſt</hi> for you; whoſe <hi>Spirit</hi> hath alſo ſealed you thereunto, and is your Pledg and Earneſt of it); and <hi>as of far greater conſequence and concernment to you, than all which you can meet with here can countervail.</hi> And, 2. it is pertinently and prudently to accommodate this your Encouragement and Support to every Exigence, ſo as to make you calm and eaſy in your ſelves, and ſenſibly and evidently pleaſed herewith, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever this your Hope may coſt you here. You muſt conſider and apply it, and regularly enforce it upon your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed Souls, and live upon it as your Food and Treaſure, and reſt herein, when little elſe but Toil and Sorrow here becomes your daily Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But I have more largely hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led this, in my printed Sermon on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.11. in Dr. <hi>Anneſlie</hi>'s <hi>Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Exerciſe,</hi> and thither I refer you, (though ill printed).</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:102539:46"/>2. Comfort one another with theſe words, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.16. 'tis needful, uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and delightful thus to do; for God hath ſet this State, thus chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteriſed before us, as our <hi>Directory,</hi> to ſhew us what we are to be and do, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2, 3. as our <hi>Encouragement</hi> hereunto, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.58. and as the <hi>Reward</hi> hereof, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.35-37. We are to give our Sentiments and Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this State, and to repreſent it in its greatneſs each to other. We are to confer about its certainty, and ſo to ſhew and ſettle the reaſons of our belief hereof, to diſcourſe the nearneſs of it, leſt otherwiſe the Midnight-Cry ſurprize us; to talk about the Means and Evidence of our being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled thereunto, and of its ſuitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to all our holy Principles and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtincts, and to the Capacities and true Welfare of our Souls, and of thoſe great and glorious Purpoſes which it may ſubſerve; and to converſe about the Snares which may be broken, and of the Miſchiefs which may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:102539:46"/> by our lively Thoughts, Belief, and Hopes, and Reliſhes of this bliſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful State; and by our warm Diſcourſe about it. And we are to quicken one another to comparative Thoughts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it; that is, to conſider it in its Tranſcendencies above all that rivals or oppoſes it. Sometimes our Mouths or Palats have loſte their taſt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh; and then Diſcourſe hereon muſt cure us; and the great Excellencies of our Lord, and of our abode with him for ever, muſt be diſplayed afreſh. Sometimes our Hearts are out of hope, and then Chriſt as our Advocate and Head in Heaven, preparing all Things for our ſolemn meeting with him, and as the Patron of this Hope, may be the proper and fit Theme for Chriſtian Conference about. Sometimes our Minds and Thoughts are vagrant, and like looſe Garments, rather hinder us than help us; and then ſome warm diſcourſe about this State may reduce our diſtracted Spirits to ſome advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous compoſures. Somtimes our Hearts
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:102539:47"/> are cold and careleſs, and then ſome applicatory Conference about this heavenly State and Priviledg, may make them burn again within us. Sometimes the frame of Spirit, and courſe of Life, which is moſt conge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial with this Lord and State, is much neglected; and we are degenerating into unchriſtian Principles, Diſpoſitions and Practices; and then to ſpeak of Chriſt in all thoſe Glories where he and we muſt dwell together, may recover us from our Decays and Lapſes. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times our Devotions have not their proper Life and Spirit in them, as Prayer, Praiſe, Thanks, Sabbath-So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnities, and Sacramental Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and Tranſactions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and then right Words warmly delivered and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced, may make our Altars flame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh. And ſometimes we are in the Houſe of Mourning; ſome ſick, ſome weak, ſome dead, and ſome twice dead, all more or leſs lamenting the mournful State of Things, Souls, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and then <hi>for ever with the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:102539:47"/> Lord</hi> cloſely diſcourſed, may afford very great relief. For Chriſt, and all his Saints with him in Glory, allays the bitterneſs of all ſuch Cups, makes all Conditions eaſy, clears up the Brow, and warms the Heart, and adds new Life and Vigour to all our Winter and Summer-Graces, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2, 3. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 2-12. and fully reconciles us to all thoſe Scenes of Sorrows, and to Death it ſelf, through which we are to come to Chriſt. Converſe then more about this thing, for no Salt like this to ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Converſation with, <hi>Col.</hi> 4.5. and nothing fitter to refreſh the drooping Soul. And therefore, <hi>Ye Beloved, build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up your ſelves (and one another) on your moſt holy Faith, praying in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, keep your ſelves in the Love of God, looking for the Mercy of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt unto Eternal Life,</hi> Jude 20, 21. <hi>Now our Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, and God even our Father, who hath loved us, and given us everlaſting Conſolation, and good Hope through
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:102539:48"/> Grace, comfort your Hearts, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh you in every good Word and Work,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 2.16, 17. <hi>And to him that is able to keep you from falling, and to preſent you faultleſs before the preſence of his Glory with exceeding Joy: To the only wiſe God our Saviour, be Glory and Majeſty, Dominion and Power, both now and ever. Amen.</hi> Jude 24, 25.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:102539:48"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
